[Music]
let A and B be two positive real numbers
first draw a square with side length a
and adjacent to that draw a square with
side length B in each Square we can draw
the diagonals and use the intersection
to draw a line from the center of the
square to the midpoint of the base of
the square this process has created
isosceles right triangles in either
square one of them with a side length of
a over two and one of them with a side
length of B over 2. now we can connect
the center points of the two squares to
create a right triangle pictured here
the legs of this right triangle are a
divided by the square root of 2 and B
divided by the square root of 2 since
both of those are hypotenuses of the
previously described right triangles but
then we can use the Pythagorean theorem
to find that the hypotenuse of this
triangle is the square root of a squared
over 2 plus b squared over two the two
isosceles right triangles and the Shaded
purple triangle create a trapezoid from
this trapezoid we see that the one side
length given by a over 2 plus b over 2
is less than or equal to the longer side
length which is given by the square root
of a squared over 2 plus b squared over
two no matter this sizes of A and B we
see that we can always create this
diagram with an a by a square and a b by
b square and a triangle connecting their
Center points this triangle is part of a
trapezoid and the trapezoid has one long
side and one short side so the
inequality is always strict except in
the one situation where the side length
a equals the side length B therefore a
over 2 plus b over 2 is less than or
equal to the square root of a squared
over 2 plus b squared over 2 and
equality occurs if and only if a equals
B A over two plus b over 2 is the
arithmetic mean of A and B and the
square root of a squared over 2 plus b
squared over 2 is the root mean square
of A and B so this is known as the
arithmetic mean root mean Square
inequality